Hello.
In this video, we'll continue to consider
some summary measures we can use when
exploring a dataset.
This time, we'll go to the data provided
by our anthropologist.
Here, we're trying to estimate age at
death from skeletal remains.
And in this video, we'll in particular
consider the method of the [UNKNOWN].
We're intrested in how well this method
works.
So, we'll consider the difference between
the estimated age, based on the skeleton,
and the actual age at death for the 400
skeletons in our dataset.
We'll begin with a look at a box plot of
these data.
Although there are some positive values,
we can see that most of the observations
are negative.
In fact, because the third quartile is
negative, we know that more than three
quarters or 75% of the data are negative.
So, the method of [UNKNOWN] tends to
underestimate the age of death.
It's also possible with this method to be
way off from the actual age.
Note that the minimum value is negative
60.
Meaning for one of the observations, the
estimate was 60 years younger than the
actual age.
We may want to investigate how unusual
this value of negative 60 is.
A modified box plot is one way to do
this.
Modified box plots were designed to
detect unusual observations.
To draw one, we first calculate the
interquartile range or IQR.
This is the difference between the third
and first quartile.
For these data, the third quartile is
negative 5 and the first quartile is
negative 23, the difference is 18, so the
interquartile range is 18.
We then locate the inner fences, which
are designed to contain most of the data.
The inner fences are the values that are
1.5 times the IQR beyond the first and
third quartile.
For the lower inner fence, then we
calculate the first quartile, negative
23, minus 1.5 times the interquartile
range, 18, which gives us negative 50.
Similarly, for the upper inner fence, we
calculate negative 5 plus 1.5 times 18
and get 22.
In a modified box plot, the whiskers
extend to the observations that are
closest to the fences but still within
them.
Values outside the fences are indicated
individually and are worthy of some
attention, particularly isolated values
that are far outside the fences.
We can see that our minimum value of
negative 60 is outside the inner fences
but there are also other observations
beyond the fences.
So, perhaps in underestimate of 60 years
is part of the range of values that might
be observed with the[UNKNOWN] method.
Here's a quick summary on how to instruct
a modified box plot.
It can help us both summarize the data
and detect some possibly unusual
observations.
Here's the five-number summary again for
our data.
The median is a measure of the center of
the data.
Another common statistic used to capture
the center of the data is the mean or
average.
We'll introduce a bit of mathematical
notation here.
The Greek letter, capital sigma, is used
in mathematics for sum.
The mean is the sum of the data values
divided by the number of data points.
Suppose we have n data points, for our
example, n is 400, the number of
skeletons.
Let's represent our data values as x
subscript 1, x subscript 2, through x
subscript n.
The subscript is an index for the
position of the data value in the
dataset, and n is the number of data
values.
The mean is given the symbol x with a bar
over it.
And the formula for the mean is the sum
sigma of the x's, from the first
observation to the last, divided by the
number of data values n.
For the differences between the estimated
and actual ages for our 400 skeletons, n
was 400, the median, as we saw, is
negative 13 and the mean for this data is
negative 14.2 .
Notice that the mean is more negative
than the median for this data.
This happens because the mean is pulled
down by the unusually large negative
observations we observed here.
We say that the mean is not a robust
statistic.
That is, it is not resistant to extreme
observations.
In contrast, the median is a robust
statistic.
Changing the values of the extreme
observations does not change the value of
the middle observation.
Suppose we wanted to limit the influence
of the extreme observations on the
calculation of the mean, one option is to
use a trimmed mean.
To find a 10% trimmed mean, delete the
largest 10% and the smallest 10% of the
data, and then take the average of the
remaining observations.
For these data, we remove the 40 largest
and smallest data values, and the 10%
trimmed mean is negative 13.8.
Note that the trimmed mean is closer to
the median than the mean, as the trimmed
mean is more robust to extreme
observations than the mean.
As an illustration of the robustness of
the median and trimmed mean versus the
mean, let's look at a smaller data set.
Here are the salaries in US dollars
announced in May, 2012, for the 25
players on the New York Red Bulls, a
soccer team in the MLS.
I've put them in order, from smallest to
largest.
As is typical in the MLS, a few players
have very large salaries, while most of
the players have salaries more in line
with the average American.
In particular, the salaries of Rafael
Marquez and Thierry Henry, who had the
largest salary in the MLS, are much
larger than the salaries of their
teammates.
You can see just how unusual Marquez and
Henry are by looking at a modified box
plot.
The box needed to be very compressed to
fit them on the screen.
Let's do some calculations.
Since there are 25 salaries, the median
is the 13th value in the ordered salaries
which is about $112,000.
For the mean, we sum the salaries and
divide by 25 to get approximately
$518,000.
We can see that the mean is much larger
than the median because it is influenced
by the large salaries of Marquez and
Henry.
If we want to remove their influence, we
can use a trimmed mean.
8% of 25 is 2.
So, an 8% trimmed mean would remove
Marquez and Henry as well as two players
earning $33,750.
The trimmed mean is the average of the 21
remaining salaries and is about $128,000,
which is a value that is much more
representative of the salaries of the
rest of the team.
Here's a summary of the measures of
center, or location, that we've
discussed.
The median and the trimmed mean are
robust against extreme observations,
while the mean is not.