Now that we've seen a few datasets and
some of the summary statistics we can
calculate and plots we can create in
order to get and understanding of our
data, we'll now summarize some of the
features of data in general.
An observational unit is the person or
thing on which measurements are taken for
which a number of different terms are
commonly used.
Examples of observational units that
we've encountered already include country
or territory and our life expectancy
data, skeleton in our anthropological
data, and soccer player in the data of
salaries of New York Red Bulls players.
When we talk about a variable, we're
talking about a characteristic that we've
measured on an observational unit.
In our life expectancy data, this
includes, of course, life expectancy, as
well as region of the world.
In our anthropological data, variables
include age at death, sex, BMI, the
estimated age at death, the difference
between the actual and estimated age at
death, which is an example of a variable
calculated from other variables, and the
salary of our soccer players.
An observed value or observation is our
data.
It is the actual value of a variable for
one of the observational units in a
dataset.
Data are arranged in rows and columns,
with one row for each observational unit
and a column for each variable.
Many different file formats are possible
for data, such as spreadsheets and comma
separated values.
If you explore the data files used in
this course, you'll find that we're
supplying the data in plain text files
with spaces separating the observed
values of the variables.
Note, as here, that categorical variables
can be coded multiple ways, including as
numbers.
Here, a sex of 1 indicates a male and 2,
a female.
It's not a quantitative variable however.
As we've already seen, variables can be
of various types.
A variable is quantitative if it takes on
numerical values for which arithmetic
operations make sense.
For a quantitative variable, saying that
one observation is twice as large as
another, has a practical meaning.
If one soccer player's salary, say, is
twice that of another, that has a clear
meaning.
Similarly, saying one soccer player's
salary is $10,000 more than another
players has a clear mathematically
precise meaning, regardless of how much
each soccer player earns.
This is characteristic of a quantitative
variable.
Some examples of quantitative variables
we've seen include life expectancy, the
actual age of a skeleton at time of
death, the estimated age for that
skeleton, the difference between those
two ages, the estimated and the actual
age, and salary of the soccer players.
A categorical variable records into which
of several categories an observation
falls.
As we saw in a previous video, we treat
categorical variables with different
summary statistics, such as relative
frequency.
Then, we use the quantitative variables.
Some examples of categorical variables
we've seen includes sex, which is
categories male or female.
BMI, when we consider it as the standard
classifications of underweight, normal,
overweight and obese.
And region of the world which had six
categories in our data.
And finally, there are ordinal variables,
which have a natural order.
Unlike quantitative variables, the
differences between two values of an
ordinal variable may not be meaningful.
Sometimes, ordinal variables are treated
as quantitative.
But when doing so, we need to be careful.
If the quantity like, say, the mean truly
makes sense.
However, if the median or middle value,
typically does make sense for an ordinal
variable.
An example of ordinal variable we've seen
is the BMI classifications.
Since underweight is less than normal,
which is less than overweight, which is
less than obese.
Another example of an ordinal variable is
the response to a Likert item on a
questionnaire, where the respondent gets
to choose from strongly disagree,
disagree, and so on, up to strongly
agree.
In earlier videos, we talked about
outliers and their effect on calculations
of summary statistics.
In the New York Red Bulls salary data,
there were two players whose salaries
were much larger than every other
player's salary on the team.
This happened as a result of the
designated player rule.
This is the defining feature of an
outlier, that it is separated from the
rest of the data.
Outliers shouldn't be ignored or
routinely removed from the data.
It can happen that an outlier is a
mistake.
In a dataset of ages, say, an age of 555
is clearly impossible and was likely a
typo.
Cleaning data by correcting errors like
this is an important first step in
dealing with a new dataset.
It's important to try to find out the
reason for unusual observations.
When outliers are not mistakes, they
might be the most interesting feature,
and removing them would remove an
important aspect of the data.
But as we've seen in previous videos,
they can sometimes have an overly
influential effect on summary statistics
that are not robust and they must be
treated with care in the analysis.
It's not unusual to report findings both
with and without outliers.
Sometimes, a dataset can include missing
values.
Observed values can be missing for a
number of reasons.
In the anthropology dataset of age
estimates from skeletal remains, we've
been looking at estimates of age at death
which were taken using the DeGangi
method.
And the data we're using a random subset
of skeletons chosen from those for which
the first rib, which we need for the
DeGangi estimate, was intact.
It's possible for any skeleton, that the
first rib might be missing or damaged so
that a DeGangi age estimate cannot be
made and the age estimate for the
skeleton would be missing.
Sometimes, the fact that a data value was
missing tells us something about what it
would have been, had it been observed.
Imagine a scale for measuring a person's
weight that only goes up to, say, 100
kilograms.
Any larger subjects who were part of the
study using this scale would have had a
missing value for their weight.
Not including them in the analyses would
bias the results by, for example, having
a mean weight that was smaller than the
actual mean weight would have been, had
the larger subjects been included.
Or imagine a study where some subjects
dropped out, because they weren't doing
well.
Carrying out analyses without these
subjects would make us think that the
subjects as a group did better than they
actually did.
These types of situations require a lot
of care.
For our skeletal remains, we don't expect
that a missing first rib has any relation
to the age of the skeleton at time of
death, or to any other features of the
skeleton, such as sex, or BMI, or to the
estimate we would have got.
It may be reasonable then to assume that
excluding skeletons for which we have a
missing value for the DeGangi age
estimate doesn't have any effect on our
analysis and we can continue to work with
the dataset without them.
But any time we encounter a dataset with
missing values, we must consider
carefully why they were missing, and
whether the fact that they're missing
might bias the results of our work.